Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Catherine and today we're talking about a very important topic.
我是Catherine，今天我们讨论一个非常重要的话题。
This is about time.
这跟时间有关。
That's right.
没错。
So sometimes we are a little bit lazy or maybe we sleep too much and we're late to work or
所以有时候我们有点懒，或者睡太多，上班迟到，
a meeting.
或者开会迟到。
All right.
好的。
So learn many different ways to talk about being late today.
所以今天学习多种谈论迟到的表达方式。
Let's take a listen to our dialogue.
我们来听一下对话。
Okay, everyone.
好了，各位。
Shall we begin?
我们可以开始了吗？
Sorry Maggie, but we're missing a few people.
抱歉Maggie，我们还有几个人没到。
Can we hang on a sec?
能稍等一下吗？
Well, I did say 11 o'clock sharp and it's now five past.
嗯，我确实说了11点整，现在已经过了五分钟了。
So...
所以……
Hi, everyone.
大家好。
I'm so sorry I'm late.
非常抱歉我迟到了。
It's raining cats and dogs outside and I had to wait ages for a taxi.
外面下着倾盆大雨，我等出租车等了很久。
Okay, James.
好的，James。
Take a seat quickly, please.
请快点坐下。
Right.
好的。
The subject of the meeting is the importance.
会议的主题是重要性。
Hi, guys.
嗨，大家好。
Please excuse me.
请原谅我。
I was held up in traffic.
我被堵在路上了。
Right.
好的。
As I was saying, the subject of the meeting is...
正如我刚才所说，会议的主题是……
Hi, Maggie.
嗨，Maggie。
I'm terribly sorry.
我非常抱歉。
The traffic is murder out there.
外面交通简直糟透了。
Sit down, Bruno.
坐下吧，Bruno。
Okay.
好的。
Now, as you're aware, the topic for the meeting is the importance of being punctual.
现在，正如你们所知，会议的主题是守时的重要性。
Who would like to start?
谁想先发言？
All right.
好的。
We're back.
我们回来了。
So now let's take a look at some of this vocab on Language Takeaway.
现在让我们看看“语言小贴士”中的一些词汇。
Language Takeaway.
语言小贴士。
So first up, we have a word that we heard.
首先，我们听到一个词。
The phrase was, I did say 11 o'clock sharp.
短语是：我确实说了11点整。
Okay.
好的。
So if you say the time, like 11 o'clock, and then you add sharp at the end, what does that
所以如果你说时间，比如11点，然后在后面加上sharp，
mean?
那是什么意思？
That means exactly.
意思是“正好”。
So, 11 o'clock, exactly 11 o'clock.
所以，11点整，正好11点。
11, zero, zero.
11点零分零秒。
Not 1101, not 1102, but 11 o'clock.
不是11点01分，也不是11点02分，而是11点整。
So if I say, I'll be there at three o'clock sharp.
所以如果我说：我会在三点整到。
That means you won't be there at 2.58.
意思是你不会在2点58分到。
You will not be there at 3.04.
你也不会在3点04分到。
You'll be there at three o'clock.
你会在三点整到。
That's right.
没错。
Okay.
好的。
So three o'clock sharp.
所以三点整。
So if you say the time and then you add sharp, it means at that exact time.
所以如果你说时间然后加上sharp，意思就是那个准确的时间。
Now James was late.
现在James迟到了。
He said he was late because he had to wait ages for a taxi.
他说他迟到是因为等出租车等了很久。
Okay.
好的。
So this might be confusing for some people, Marco, because I can say, what's your age?
这可能让一些人困惑，Marco，因为我可以问：你多大年纪？
How old are you?
你几岁？
But here, ages has a different meaning.
但在这里，ages有不同的意思。
So I had to wait ages means I waited a very long time.
所以“我等了很久”意思是我等了很长时间。
That's right.
没错。
So the word ages means for a very long time.
所以单词ages意思是“很长时间”。
It's always related to time in this sense.
在这个语境下，它总是和时间相关。
Exactly.
正是。
So I could say, Marco, it's so good to see you.
所以我可以这样说：Marco，见到你真好。
I haven't seen you in ages.
我好久没见到你了。
That means I haven't seen you in such a long time.
意思是我很久没见到你了。
Okay.
好的。
Very good.
很好。
And now the next person, Sally came in and she said she was held up in traffic.
现在下一个人，Sally进来了，她说她被堵在路上了。
Okay.
好的。
So to be held up in traffic means to be stuck in traffic.
所以“被堵在路上”意思是“被困在交通中”。
That means you were made late because there were so many cars on the road.
意思是你因为路上车太多而迟到了。
Okay.
好的。
So somebody or something else made you late.
所以是某人或某事让你迟到了。
That's right.
没错。
So to be held up means to be made late.
所以“被耽搁”意思是“被弄迟了”。
I could ask you, Marco, why are you so late?
我可以问你，马可，你为什么这么晚？
What held you up?
什么耽误了你？
Exactly.
没错。
What held you up?
什么耽误了你？
That means what made me late.
意思是让我迟到的原因。
That's right.
对。
It could be many different things.
可能有很多不同的原因。
Okay.
好的。
Yeah.
嗯。
It could be traffic or maybe I could be held up by the doctor.
可能是交通，或者我可能被医生耽误了。
Maybe he took longer than what I expected.
也许他花的时间比我预期的长。
Or there's no elevator and I'm waiting for the elevator and I got held up by the elevator.
或者没有电梯，我在等电梯，结果被电梯耽误了。
Okay.
好的。
Very good.
很好。
And now the importance of being punctual.
现在来说说准时的重要性。
That's the topic of the meeting.
这是会议的主题。
And so what is this word, punctual?
那么，这个词“准时”是什么意思？
Okay.
好的。
So punctual is an adjective and it describes something as being on time.
“准时”是一个形容词，用来描述某事是准时的。
Okay.
好的。
So the opposite of this word would be what?
那么这个词的反义词是什么？
So the opposite would be late.
反义词是“迟到”。
Late.
迟到。
Okay.
好的。
So she's a very punctual student.
她是一个非常准时的学生。
She always comes to class on time.
她总是准时来上课。
She's never late.
她从不迟到。
Punctual.
准时。
So you describe a person as being punctual or not.
所以你可以形容一个人是否准时。
That's right.
对。
Okay.
好的。
Very good.
很好。
Let's review all this vocab.
我们来复习一下这些词汇。
Let's go back and listen to the dialogue again.
我们回去再听一遍对话。
Okay, everyone, shall we begin?
好的，各位，我们可以开始了吗？
Sorry, Maggie, but we're missing a few people.
抱歉，玛吉，我们还缺几个人。
Can we hang on a sec?
我们能稍等一下吗？
Well, I did say 11 o'clock sharp and it's now five past.
嗯，我确实说了11点整，现在已经过了五分钟。
So...
所以……
Hi, everyone.
大家好。
I'm so sorry I'm late.
非常抱歉我迟到了。
It's raining cats and dogs outside and I had to wait ages for a taxi.
外面下着倾盆大雨，我等出租车等了很久。
Okay, James.
好的，詹姆斯。
Take a seat quickly, please.
请快点坐下。
Right.
好的。
The subject of the meeting is the importance...
会议的主题是重要性……
Hi, guys.
嗨，大家好。
Please excuse me.
请原谅我。
I was held up in traffic.
我被交通堵住了。
Right.
好的。
As I was saying, the subject of the meeting is...
正如我刚才说的，会议的主题是……
Hi, Maggie.
嗨，玛吉。
I'm terribly sorry.
我非常抱歉。
The traffic is murder out there.
外面的交通简直要命。
Sit down, Bruno.
坐下吧，布鲁诺。
Okay, now, as you're aware, the topic for the meeting is the importance of being punctual.
好的，现在，正如你们所知，会议的主题是准时的重要性。
Who would like to start?
谁想先发言？
All right.
好的。
Now let's take a look at some phrases on Fluency Builder.
现在让我们看看“流利度构建器”中的一些短语。
Fluency Builder.
流利度构建器。
We have a lot of really great phrases today that describe...
我们今天有很多很棒的短语，用来描述……
Well, that are excuses for not being on time or for not being punctual.
嗯，就是那些为不准时或不守时找的借口。
The first one we heard was actually different, though.
不过，我们听到的第一个短语其实不一样。
One of the students said, can we hang on a sec?
其中一个学生说：“我们能稍等一下吗？”
Hang on a sec.
稍等一下。
Okay.
好的。
So, if you ask someone to hang on, that means to wait.
所以，如果你让别人“hang on”，意思是等待。
Hang on.
等一下。
Wait.
等待。
Yeah, exactly.
嗯，没错。
So, hang on just means to wait.
所以，“hang on”就是等待的意思。
It's very casual.
这很随意。
Okay.
好的。
So, if you ask someone to hang on a sec, hang on a sec or hang on a minute, that means wait
所以，如果你让别人“hang on a sec”、“hang on a sec”或“hang on a minute”，意思是等
for a little while.
一小会儿。
A little while.
A sec, S-E-C, stands for second.
“a sec”，S-E-C，代表“second”（秒）。
And it's very common in this phrase.
这个短语很常见。
We hear, hang on a sec or wait a sec.
我们经常听到“hang on a sec”或“wait a sec”。
Wait a sec.
等一下。
Uh-huh.
嗯哼。
Okay, very good.
好的，非常好。
So, it's very casual.
所以，这非常随意。
It's very spoken English, although the word sec doesn't really exist.
这是很口语化的英语，尽管“sec”这个词并不真正存在。
It's just a short way of saying a second.
它只是“a second”的简短说法。
Exactly.
没错。
And later on, we heard James come in, he was one of those people that we had to wait for,
后来，我们听到詹姆斯进来了，他是我们不得不等的人之一，
and he said, it's raining cats and dogs outside.
他说，外面下着倾盆大雨。
That's right.
对。
Okay.
好的。
It's raining cats and dogs.
下着倾盆大雨。
So, are cats and dogs falling from the sky?
所以，猫和狗真的从天上掉下来了吗？
They are not.
不是的。
So, this might sound very weird to you.
所以，这听起来可能很奇怪。
This does not mean there are cats and dogs falling down from the clouds, but it does
这并不意味着有猫和狗从云上掉下来，而是
mean that it's raining a lot.
意味着雨下得很大。
It's raining really hard outside.
外面雨下得真大。
Okay, very good.
好的，非常好。
So, it's a phrase used to say it's raining a lot.
所以，这是一个用来表示雨下得很大的短语。
It's raining very, very hard.
雨下得非常非常大。
Raining cats and dogs.
倾盆大雨。
So, Maggie is trying to continue with the meeting as many people keep coming in and
所以，玛吉试图继续开会，但很多人不断进来
disrupting her.
打断她。
So, she says, right, as I was saying, the subject of the meeting.
所以，她说，对，正如我刚才说的，会议的主题。
As I was saying.
正如我刚才说的。
Now, this is a really important phrase because you're going to hear this a lot in meetings
现在，这是一个非常重要的短语，因为你在会议中
or in conversations where someone is distracted.
或有人被打断的对话中会经常听到。
So, okay, we're having, oh wait.
所以，好的，我们正在，哦等等。
I'm sorry, I have to talk to this person over here.
对不起，我得和这边的人说句话。
When you want to come back to what you were talking about, you want to return to the topic,
当你想回到你之前谈论的内容时，你想回到话题上，
you say, as I was saying.
你就说，正如我刚才说的。
That's right.
对。
As I was saying.
正如我刚才说的。
So, maybe you were interrupted, maybe you got distracted and you want to continue talking
所以，也许你被打断了，也许你分心了，你想继续谈论
about the same topic as I was saying and then you continue talking.
同一个话题，就像我刚才说的，然后你继续讲。
So, you return to the original point you are making.
所以，你回到你最初的观点。
Okay, very good.
好的，非常好。
And well, Bruno was the last guy to come in and he said that traffic is murder out there.
嗯，布鲁诺是最后一个进来的人，他说外面交通糟透了。
Okay, so murder, to murder means to kill someone.
好的，所以“murder”，谋杀意味着杀死某人。
But we're not talking about killing people here.
但我们这里不是在谈论杀人。
We're talking about an analogy.
我们是在做一个类比。
We're saying it's as bad as murder.
我们说它糟糕得像谋杀一样。
So, in this case, traffic is murder means traffic is really awful.
所以，在这种情况下，“traffic is murder”意味着交通非常糟糕。
It's really terrible outside.
外面真的很糟糕。
So, in what other situation or with what other noun instead of traffic can we use this something
那么，在什么其他情况下，或者用其他什么名词代替“traffic”，我们可以用这个“something
is murder?
is murder”？
The wait is murder.
等待是折磨。
Okay.
好的。
So, that means you have to wait a very, very long time.
所以，那意味着你必须等非常非常久。
Okay.
好的。
All right, very good.
好的，非常好。
So, now why don't we go back to the dialogue.
那么，现在我们为什么不回到对话呢？
Let's have one last review and we'll be right back.
让我们做最后一次回顾，然后马上回来。
Okay, everyone, shall we begin?
好的，各位，我们可以开始了吗？
Sorry, Maggie, but we're missing a few people.
抱歉，玛吉，我们还缺几个人。
Can we hang on a sec?
我们能等一会儿吗？
Well, I did say 11 o'clock sharp and it's now five past.
嗯，我确实说了11点整，现在已经过了五分钟。
So, hi, everyone.
所以，大家好。
I'm so sorry I'm late.
非常抱歉我迟到了。
It's raining cats and dogs outside and I had to wait ages for a taxi.
外面下着倾盆大雨，我等出租车等了很久。
Okay, James, take a seat quickly, please.
好的，詹姆斯，请快点坐下。
Right, the subject of the meeting is the importance.
对，会议的主题是重要性。
Hi, guys.
嗨，大家好。
Please excuse me.
请原谅我。
I was held up in traffic.
我被交通堵住了。
Right.
对。
As I was saying, the subject of the meeting is...
正如我刚才说的，会议的主题是……
Hi, Maggie.
嗨，玛吉。
I'm terribly sorry.
我非常抱歉。
The traffic is murder out there.
外面交通糟透了。
Sit down, Bruno.
坐下，布鲁诺。
Okay, now.
好的，现在。
As you're aware, the topic for the meeting is the importance of being punctual.
正如你们所知，会议的主题是守时的重要性。
Who would like to start?
谁想先发言？
So, Marco, are you a punctual person or are you usually late?
那么，马可，你是一个守时的人，还是通常迟到？
For social gatherings, I'm usually pretty punctual.
对于社交聚会，我通常很守时。
For work, I'm usually very late.
对于工作，我通常很晚。
I've noticed.
我注意到了。
You're one of the last people to come in in the morning.
你是早上最后到的人之一。
Yeah, usually for work, I arrive late but not like too late.
是的，通常上班我会迟到，但不会太晚。
Some people may even be an hour or two or something.
有些人甚至可能迟到一两个小时之类的。
A couple minutes, 15 minutes is all right.
迟到几分钟、十五分钟还可以接受。
But I do hate to wait.
但我确实讨厌等人。
If we agree to meet up at 2 o'clock and you come in at 2.30, I don't know, let's say to
如果我们约好两点见面，你两点半才来，我不知道，比如说
the movies, then I think that's really irritating.
去看电影，那我觉得这真的很烦人。
I agree.
我同意。
I'm a very punctual person and I get very annoyed when people are late to meetings or
我是一个非常守时的人，当人们开会迟到时，我会很恼火，
when people come late to appointments or parties.
或者当人们约会或派对迟到时。
And I think it's different in different countries because in many different places, they have
而且我认为这在不同的国家是不同的，因为在很多不同的地方，他们有
what they call the local time.
所谓的“当地时间”。
So if you say, okay, the meeting is at 9, then everyone assumes that the meeting is
所以如果你说，好吧，会议九点开始，那么每个人都以为会议
supposed to start at 9 but then everyone comes in at 9 but grabs a cup of coffee, talks
应该在九点开始，但每个人九点到了之后，会先喝杯咖啡，在饮水机旁聊天，
at the cooler, gets their seat, checks their email and then the meeting will start at 9.30
找到座位，查看邮件，然后会议实际上要到九点半才开始，
instead of 9.
而不是九点。
Right.
没错。
Or for example, the transportation you will find in different countries can be punctual
或者举个例子，你会发现不同国家的交通系统可能守时
or not punctual.
也可能不守时。
In Germany, their transportation is very famous for being punctual.
在德国，他们的交通系统以守时著称。
But in India, you will find that the trains are not very punctual.
但在印度，你会发现火车不太守时。
You might wait one or two or six hours for a train.
你可能要等一两个小时，甚至六个小时才能等到火车。
Yeah, exactly.
是的，完全正确。
So it's different in different countries.
所以不同国家情况不同。
I imagine that in a place like Germany, it would be considered a very bad thing to arrive
我想在像德国这样的地方，开会迟到会被认为是非常不好的行为，
late to a meeting, for example.
比如说。
Yeah, I'm curious about that.
是的，我对此很好奇。
So let us know, is it acceptable in your country to be a little bit late to a meeting or to
所以请告诉我们，在你的国家，开会或赴约迟到一点点是可以接受的吗？
an appointment?
Is punctuality important?
守时重要吗？
Let us know.
请告诉我们。
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
我们的网站是 EnglishPod.com。
All right.
好了。
We'll see you guys there.
我们会在那里见你们。
Thanks for watching.
感谢观看。